Guide to the Captain O.C. McDavid World War II Letters
University of Houston Libraries
Captain O.C. McDavid World War II Letters
1943-1945
2011-008
McDavid, O. C., 1911-1998
2.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection primarily consists of correspondence from Captain O.C. McDavid during his service in World War II in the South Pacific.
Biographical Information:
O.C. McDavid was born on May 30, 1911 in Ruth, Mississippi. At the urging of his high school English teacher, McDavid forged a non-traditional path into a career in the newspaper industry. He secured his first job sweeping up the print shop at the Enterprise Journal while in high school. As his responsibilities grew to include running the print shop as well as writing, he attended high school part-time so that he could pursue his new career full-time.
McDavid’s career took an unexpected turn as the United States’ involvement in World War II became imminent. As a member of the National Guard, McDavid received his federal induction and was quickly tapped to publish a camp newspaper named The Dixie. After the Japanese bombing of Pearl Harbor, McDavid was stationed in the South Pacific. There, in New Guinea, McDavid was placed in charge of establishing village governments with the local population and helped to provide local services such as sanitation, security, and health.
Following the war, McDavid returned to the newspaper industry, finally retiring at the age of 70. He turned his time and energies to sculpting and painting, earning the George Ohr Public Service Award (honoring Mississippians who have supported crafts as art) in 1976.
He died on March 12, 1998 in Jackson, Mississippi. The following year the Mississippi Press Association established an annual student journalism conference in his name.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Programs (documents); Sketches
Personal Name:
McDavid, O. C., 1911-1998
Topical Term:
World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Pacific Area
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Gene McDavid, June 2, 2011
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Digitized Materials:
Captain O.C. McDavid World War II Letters digital collection (http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/mcdav)
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily consists of correspondence from Captain O.C. McDavid during his service in World War II in the South Pacific. The collection also includes a handful of correspondence addressed to Captain McDavid, newsletters from his service, memorabilia collected while abroad, a sketch drawn by Captain McDavid, newspaper clippings, and Letters from OC: The War Years--1940 through 1945, compiled by Gene McDavid.
Correspondence from Captain McDavid is arranged chronologically while letters addressed to Captain McDavid have been arranged alphabetically by author. The remaining materials have been arranged chronologically.
Detailed List of Contents
- Correspondence from Captain O.C. McDavid, 1943-1945, undated
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence from Captain O.C. McDavid is arranged chronologically and primarily focuses on his tour of duty in the South Pacific during World War II. Many of the letters are illustrated with cartoons and drawings.
  - Correspondence, September-October 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, February 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, March 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, April 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, April 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, June 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, July 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, August 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, August 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, September 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, October 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, November 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, December 1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, January 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, March 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, April 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, April 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, May 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, May 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, June 1945, August 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to Captain O.C. McDavid, 1944
  Correspondence addressed to Captain O.C. McDavid is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Newsletters
  Newsletters and a fragment of a newsletter collected by Captain O.C. McDavid during his tour of duty are arranged chronologically.
  - Newsletters, 1944-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Memorabilia
  Memorabilia include items acquired by Captain O.C. McDavid during his time abroad serving in World War II.
  - Memorabilia, 1944-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Sketch
  Included is a sketch drawn by Captain O.C. McDavid depicting facilities constructed in their military camp.
  - Sketch of facilities, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Newspaper Clippings
  Clippings include portions of articles related to soldiers in World War II, including a portion of a letter from Captain O.C. McDavid, and a cartoon.
  - Clippings, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Compilation of Materials
  Binder, assembled by O.C. McDavid’s son, includes photocopies of the various items in the collection as well as some items unavailable as originals in the collection.
  - Letters from OC: The War Years--1940 through 1945, compiled by Gene McDavid (Box 3, Item 1)